Lucas de Oliveira Gelape

Political scientist and data analyst. I have experience with analysis of political institutions, research design, and analysis of political, socioeconomic, and social media data. I have also graduated in Law and was a full-time graduate student for four years.

Education

University of São Paulo

PhD in Political Science 2017–Currently

Harvard University

Visiting Fellow 09/2019–02/2020

Federal University of Minas Gerais

MA in Political Science 2015–2017

Federal University of Minas Gerais

Bachelor in Laws 2010–2014

Professional Experience

Volt Data Lab

Oata Analyst

Feb. 2019-Aug. 2019; Jun. 2020-Currently

Participated in projects that involved data collection, analyses, and visualization, from many different sources. Currently, my focus is developing *Science Pulse*, a social listening platform, which monitors the scientific community on social media, especially on Twitter; and data analyses for stories published on *Núcleo Jornalismo*. Developed software for data collection of electoral polls, gun shootings, and local journalism in Brazil, and have also analyzed data on elections, public opinion, indigenous lands, and the podcast market.

G1 (Rede Globo)

Data Scientist

Jul. 2018-Nov. 2018

Organized data for special stories, analyzed data, and wrote news stories on politics, especially about the Brazilian general elections. Most of them were published in the "Election in Numbers" (Eleição em Números) section, and were about many topics, including campaign and party finance, female candidates quotas, reelection, polls, candidate and electorate profile and electoral results.

Instructor and teaching assistance to courses on programming and quantitative methods

Teaching experience

2017–2019

As an instructor, taught the following courses: *Introduction to Statistics* (using R) (Modus-UFMG, 2019), *Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis* (Meios-UFMG, 2017), and *Introduction to R* (UFMG Law School, 2017). As a teaching assistant, participated on the following courses: *Introduction to R* and *Collecting and analyzing web data with R* (MQ - UFMG, 2017).

Languages

English: Proficient.Italian: Advanced.Spanish: Intermediate.

Technical Skills

o Programming Languages:

R: Advanced.SQL: Beginner.TeX: Beginner.Stata: Beginner.

Softwares:

QGis: Intermediate.ArcGis: Beginner.

Courses and Training

Methodology:

- Survey Research Design (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Survey Research Analysis (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Introduction to Survey Experiments (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Field Research: Interviewing and Mixed Methods (IPSA-USP, 2018)
- Basics of Spatial Interdepence in Theory and Practice (IPSA-USP, 2018)
- Aggregate Data Analysis (MQ-UFMG, 2016)
- Spatial Data Analysis and Visualization (MQ-UFMG, 2016)
- Linear Regression (MQ-UFMG, 2015)